[music]
teaching Seya Welcome to MRI Rome
means Steps on the
path this is for
me I was
having lunch with my butt and So I was having lunch with
my mother
she passed away already and she
had a boyfriend whom she then
sent away this is what you should do with
guys she sent him away
and so we were white
and
and She asked What is the best book
in the world I love books and it was difficult for me
to choose but I think
today we are studying the greatest book on the
planet in this world the greatest book
This is what I think and my teacher taught it to me
three times it took 30
years Each time when he finished he started it
again
he taught it in two different
places one group was in Washington the
second group was near New York
I was his
driver so
I went to both places and I listened to how
he taught for 30 years and my God
how beautiful it is it It is wonderful
to study this thing and it will become a wonderful
friend to you in your life so keep
this book close to Sem I know that there is a
good translation of this book there  good
english translation i helped
translate this version so keep
this book close to you use it and
i started teaching it 14 years ago and i
promised that i would
finish it if i survive a few more days
then i will finish it and by doing so i will keep
my
promise we will finish this book
this week after 14 years of hard hard
work so lets give
ourselves a clap the
tradition of this lineage if you are in
the audience you must teach you must
be the one who teaches the next i
say strongly i am not joking i
know you haven't come to every class for
14 years i don't know at all
except me
but that's the case if i start
crying i beg you we will finish it
this week so please please
please teach it from
other
people my work is finished this
week it will be finished on this book
and then it will be your responsibility
you must teach it you should teach it even if
you weren't here the whole time that's
okay you can listen to the recording or
audio or you can
read it's not that hard okay if
you were in class but still i expect
you to teach all the books just
try to do it
mri we just try to the best of our
ability None of us are Buddha
Maybe we are not all We are not perfect
so we just have to try
so try teach it to your
students your friends I taught this
book to my wife
and my wife's mother if I could
do it then you can too
well we will finish this book this
week
Inshallah If everything goes well the
whole
[music]
book consists
of sheets it is somewhere around 6000
pages in English and we are very
close to finishing this book
when I started 14 years ago the
last part of the book was about eating about
meditation How to do meditation I thought
it would be a good strategy to first
teach the end of this book 14 years
ago about Shama Isha shnu about meditation about
deep
meditation and that's why I taught this
first because you have to
meditate on every step of the path the book
is called Steps on the Path and every time
you are taught one step then you
have to meditate on it so
it seemed logical to me
if I first teach meditation
What is the end of the book and then
look at the whole book and then everyone will be able to
meditate on each part of this book. This is the
tradition and we have come a long way,
we have looked at the three foundations, three
parts of this book, these are the different
intentions
of the motivation for which people study this
[music]
book, some
people study this book because they
want to stay away from the lower
birth
places, and they have the motivation I don’t want to
go down, fall down after my
death,
and it’s a very
unusual idea to start
this course, to get on this course, you
must start thinking about what will happen to you
after death, and this is an unusual thing in this
world, here at Prisko University there is not a
single course where they talk about how,
but everyone dies, and everyone should know
how to die. This is the most important thing,
one of the important things in this life, and that’s why
this book begins on the
day you die, and then you
go deeper and deeper, deeper, and that’s why the
lowest motivation after my death is
I don’t
want to go to the lower
worlds, I want to at least remain human.
Everyone thinks that they will be human in the
next life, firstly. In my part of the
world, in the western part of the world, we don’t believe
that you  live after death we do not believe in
life after death We do not even believe in this
And those people who believe in life
after death they say to
Nadya I will have the same amount of hair as
when I return and Volo
all people think this way but to
return as a human to this
world it is a rare thing one in a
billion if there are eight people in this room
they will return as humans this is very good
this is a very rare thing so the purpose of this
book is first to return as a
human and then at least
program Maybe you can find your
old
kimono
well This is the most minimal motivation
the lowest motivation and the second
motivation I do not want to
return where I have to die I do not
want to return to a place where I have to
lose my family again lose
my mother again I do not
I cling to a place where we do not have
such problems this is the second motivation And the
third motivation I would like to become a Buddha
because Buddha can really
help an
infinite number of people on all
planets there is no number this is an unlimited
amount this is very very fun I
think this is a very serious thing to become a
Buddha I also think that it is very very  It's a
fascinating thing I really
like helping people Today I was in a
coffee shop I cleaned up the coffee shops for the
workers
and I liked it And now
imagine that you can definitely
help billions of billions of creatures
If you can babysit the entire planet
This is
my dream I imagine that I am
sitting with my wife somewhere above the
clouds sometimes we babysit with our granddaughter she is
years old I hope
she is
she we will bring her during the cherry
blossom season so if the cherry blossoms do not bloom I will be
here until they bloom when
we arrive in the spring and it is so difficult with a
two-year-old She is so cute we
bought a school bus this size in
America all school buses for children
in America are yellow we bought her a
toy school You can
remove the top part here is the roof of this
bus and inside there are little
children and the two-year-old places these
children on the bus there is one child per room
she places the children like this and
then she gets on this bus It is so
cute  she's like that
her name is
[ __ ] she says [ __ ] passengers [ __ ]
passengers and she's trying to get on this
bus with
others this means she thinks that she's
this small
even only her leg only her leg
can fit on there she's trying
But even taking care of one dhm is a difficult
job for a
grandfather And when all the women leave and
only the grandfather remains with the child he's
like and now Imagine 8 billion
people now Imagine that you
nchi with 8 billion but I like it
I'm ready I'm waiting for
this I work very hard to become a
nanny for 8 billion people
you get to the head office of
Buddha and they give you a planet they highlight
places which is my planet this is your
planet Okay I'm ready I'll take care
of this planet and then you watch
watch the whole planet I think it's
cool this is absolute lamrim this is
motivation - This is the last motivation the
highest motivation of time I want to
babysit and about the whole planet about all the
creatures of this planet I want to make sure
that they do not grow old and do not  died if
someone dies on my planet I'm not the
best Buddha I want
Jasmine here
Jasmine her Planet her group like the whole planet
And now she thinks So I
need to do even more
and take care of the whole planet and
here we are in this part We are in this part at the
end of the book We learn how to nurse the
whole planet and there are Six famous perfect famous
activities of bahi
satva bahi satva is the one who
says I want to nurse from this
planet you make such a
decision You don't just think about your
family or your
country you want to take care of the whole
planet the
whole world it sounds difficult but it's not
I think a two year old child It's
much more difficult and the whole planet is
easier what I want to say it's very
exciting it's a lot of fun it's
great to help others not to die
but also Here personally for I really
like to have fun every day I do
Yas I want to say to be
bass this is the coolest
thing you are all too
serious about death save the planet from
death it feels like some kind of Swarm  You have to
behave like this, feel like this is a
big party and enjoy, have
fun, this is the coolest party,
take care of others, and you don't feel
like you're stressed, you're like this, but it's easy. Give
me another planet in the background, one
planet is not enough for me, and we're learning how to
do this, and we're learning. We started and we'll
continue. So, six activities
should be learned, learn these activities,
and the first is called giving. Say
yes, this is perfection, giving, we completed
it, and now we're on the second one. Repeat, sew,
this is morality and
ethics, and
let's go. By the way, I'm proud that everyone
returned after yesterday. I thought
that some people would go to
Tokyo. Yesterday was very difficult. Yesterday was a
very difficult lesson, and I'm proud that
you returned. I'm very happy that you
returned. In fact, there was a
test yesterday, if people had left yesterday
and hadn't come, they wouldn't have returned, so
we made the first lesson very difficult, and
then, well, I don't
know, it's not serious. People will give up and
leave, and in the second lesson we conduct a
real lesson, a real lesson,
and I'll show you now.
Place the seeds of your mind, don't study it.
Think about it
Okay, I'm sowing these seeds for your
next
life and you
think you don't
Learn it but you will learn I agree
maybe you won't learn it in this life but
I'm sowing Semin for the next life that's why
I'm now being told to
learn it in one week how to
read it and other ordinary people can't
so don't worry don't take it don't
take it seriously it's an
unusual language state as a linguist
who studies languages ​​this
language there is an ancient
tradition that this language fell from the
sky I believe in this
linvi it's not related to any language in the
world it's an absolutely strange
language very
unusual and it's very suitable for
Buddhism for teaching
Buddhism and well Let's go I'll
pronounce And don't you worry
Don't be upset
It's not that your schoolchildren don't
come back I'm pron for next time it
will be easier to look after you
next time if I planted some
seeds this time that's why but don't get
hung up on this
how we practice perfection
perfection of
morality perfection is a very
difficult word like that  with a
catch Nate
[music]
gim
Say
horo this is a very strange word because
it is perfection But this is not what
perfection means in this case your
morality is perfect you never get
angry at anyone you never
stole 5 dollars from your mother I
did Once
something that you did when you were a
child here is
the idea you are
perfect this does not mean what it
means if you try
it will lead you to busty and this
perfection this is what makes you
perfect this is not perfection What
makes you perfect
[music]
it is
perfection because we want to become
perfect and
pa in Sanskrit ferry
means the far side of the ocean If you are a
sphere like ro in
Los Angeles
and there is a big storm and you can sail into the
ocean and
your board reaches Japan this is
another country the farthest side of the
ocean in English the word
exit
this means to go out and
means to enter and that is
why paramita it
means to enter another
part to enter another part this is the
second perfection and that is when I teach
lamrim the steps on the path to Me  I like to
use
pictures I
call them these are pictures that
represent ideas and I call them short
and I I like to show a picture and
then teach the meaning of this picture and
later when you teach your students
starting next week
the picture will help remember attention
what helps you remember pictures are
very very useful Yes one picture we
say one picture is worth a thousand
words and here it is a picture
photograph
Yeah I call
the decision theseiz
throw out the trash What does this mean
then a book is quoted that is
called Avatar What does it mean how to live how to
become a nanny of the
planet How to
become a book with instructions on how to
become a nanny
it translates these days it was
written years
ago and I will read it for
you this is a very important word remember Repeat
pom Sam means
mind sum means mind and po means
the decision to refuse something po the
decision to refuse something for
example You can po meat can
refuse to eat meat make a decision not to
eat meat I don't want to be
involved
I don't want to participate in this I don't want to
be one of those this is not who I want to
become so
eat meat refuse to eat meat my
teacher
he you they eat a lot of meat They
say We can't  We grow vegetables
too high in the mountains, so we eat
meat. So anyway. Then I lived in a
monastery, I gave up meat. And at that
time, everyone ate meat.
And it was a little difficult for me
when my teacher introduced me to
other teachers. Oh, this is this.
Mike, he gave up eating meat, but he did
n't give up his negative thoughts.
He made fun of me every time. I said, "Okay,
and then I'll
tell you when he was 75.
Well, not that old, actually, he's
75.
He needed
surgery, but he came home from the
hospital and
said, "I'll give up meat." And I was his
cook. I didn't eat meat, but I
cooked meat for him every day, and he said, "MSO," and I said, "
Why are you feeling bad?" He said, "
No, he had surgery." Now I
know what that means, and after that, he did
n't eat meat at all, he
made fun of me for 30 years, and in the end, he said, "You know,
I think I'll give up meat, I'm like, what is
that called?" Repeat
[music]
People, so I made a decision
that I don't want to harm other
people anymore.  I won't do this anymore I will
try very hard not to harm
other people sometimes if you have some kind of
severe pain for example you go to the
hospital and your doctor is reconstructing your
stomach he cuts it open then you have an
animal and so on that's why it happens very
often
you feel sad
you feel suffering When you have
severe
suffering and then you finally
wake up I don't want to create
suffering for others I want to help them I don't
want to kill them I don't want them to be
cut open so to refuse here is
the decision
to refuse to harm other people this is the
second perfection this is the second
perfection
strength morality
ethics I'm
tired And then there is such a very beautiful
and we'll get
there repeat
[music]
they gave me a screen like this
Repeat very very very famous f
600 years ago wrote the most
famous
sa famous
conclusion on morality in
fact one
of the
translators has been translating this for 5
years she
completed the comments the
comments are very complex and she
completed Therefore in his local poetry son
Kapa
says the definition
Morality, definition of morality,
ethics, definition of the second, completely
here, here,
this
means When you decide to
refuse to harm other people, this is
morality.
And then, what is very
interesting,
traditionally, in the
Ancient schools,
morality is physical and
verbal. I will not kill. I will not
steal. I will not have sex with
another person's partner. These are
physical things, and then verbally, oral.
I will not
lie. I will not say rude things. I
will not gossip. I will not separate.
And these
seven. Three relates to the body.
Four, four, relates to the grade. Which is more
difficult? I think it seems to me that what we
do with our mouth, therefore, to refuse
these
seven is an ancient, ancient, ancient form of
morality, but something is missing.
What you do in your
mind. The ancient form of Buddhist
morality, they
say and do. And when he taught this,
he
said,
Repeat together with the
basis. The most
maternal reason, the
deepest reason, is that this is what you
think, you cannot remove it from the
perfection of morality.
What you do is moral. What you
say is moral, but in
Buddhism  The most important part of
morality is what you
think and
you can violate your
morality but no one
around you will know about it because in your mind you
can think terrible things when we are
surprised wow
I didn't think that I could think of such
terrible things Sometimes thoughts arise in
your mind
I want for example to run over this person with a
big car Oh
God sometimes your mind thinks terrible things
but you never say it you
never do it but your thoughts
think it It's a secret No one knows about it
but this is also morality in
Buddhism
So a very famous very very
famous addition to
harm people with your body to
harm people with your words and the thoughts
that are behind it he speaks very clearly about
this
decide to give up these things
this is
moral tell me who does
this mean to meditate there it may be
simple or does it mean to
meditate If you remove and this
means to get used to something The Tibetan
word for
meditation is
this comes from an ancient word
that means to get used to something
so we say that the deep meaning of
meditation is to get used to doing something in a
certain way  So this is called
meditation in ancient times also in Sanskrit
Say
Vana Havana means Hava means to be
Ana
means to
do this means it leads you to
something new and this is the meaning of the
Sanskrit word for Sanskrit Vana and it
means this to make you someone
new This is a very beautiful word and in
Tibetan the same meaning combo here it
says perfection perfection
morality is when you
do something very well You become You are
very good at being careful
not to harm others you are super careful
this is morality and this is ethics and he
gives a
definition here And
now after you give a
definition you give different types there are
types of morality in Buddhism there are three types of
morality In general Buddhism
there are three types of
morality I have a lot of friends here
from different projects that we do And it's
so
fun to talk about
Buddhism the feeling is very
pleasant just in this
room It's like It's like getting out of
prison there are three
seen
your comes from the ancient root shil What does it
mean
to feel  Refreshing Cool Today
I was walking around the city It was a day of
shila not very not very hot not very
cold This is very it's
so nice Such a coolness like a
fresh apple such a
pleasant feeling Here and here the real
meaning
is to calm your
mind freeze your bad thoughts this is
called
shila here he says that shila has
three types and the first type is the most basic type of
Buddhist
morality is do not harm other
people there are levels
and the first level of morality
is even if you ca
n't If you can't give another
your hand at least you should not harm
other people this is
called the first type of morality do not
harm other
people and then he
Dat he says
Now I have
finances I gave all my money yesterday we have
something
left he is a
magician money
will get it no big deal there is
money Let's find some there are
hundreds there Let's a
hundred I need more investors
[music]
I'm not asking for money I'm really not
asking for money I just need to go to the bank
he
says
equality don't harm other people there is no
taste like chocolate does
not harm others  lum it has three
flavors three shades all three all
three all three types of classic dinners they They
they have this one
in  this taste so
therefore Name these three traditional
three traditional types of atov they all
have this this is the basis but do not shout but
raise your hand I give money to those who Yes
raise your hand so the person who has the
microphone chooses who
answers You can turn on
the microphone loudly
speak directly Kiss the microphone very close
against so 66
dollars and the Diamond Way vows yes 100
dollars Buddhist
vows they have three flavors like chocolate
Vani and
strawberry first
called sum to harm
vows these are vows ba these are very interesting
vows bahi
they promise 64 Promises that you make
until the end of your life to help other
people be good to other
people the first level just do not harm
other people the first level
control yourself and the second level
is the Network seeds in your own mind to
become Nika of the planet
[music]
bai I talked about this yesterday we we
will have a ceremony about here some of my
friends asked me to take vows
pos I usually don't do this I usually
bring in
contractors here it's called Nana I think
and this is the place where  where where are the first one
of the first Chinese masters who
came from Japan his
name is
repeat that
guy He tried to come to
Japan six times five times his ship
wrecked the rudder and got into a wreck and then the
sixth time he came and the first thing he
did was he went to the
emperor and his friends and made vows to save
this temple does VS still exist This is a
very beautiful place I was there with my
friends and I
thought I thought it would be great to give
there about in the
exact place where he
stood it will be in March
when the saku flowers open the basa will
open
we we determine the date and also we need
special permission from
the state from the state But if they
don't give us permission we will then do it
next to the hotel which is nearby on the
beach of this hotel so don't move
This is the second
type now secret vows these are bahi vows
How how can you say these are such super
charged bahi vows these are super
bahi vows You want to know how my teacher
presented these
vows and as the teacher said the third type of
vow is secret and they are
secret
but I will teach them in  next year
and so he says I will now quote for
you
Asha this is a famous
book that was written exactly a thousand
years ago exactly
years this means light on the path of Buvi
and he
says very well known
definitions of different
types of morality of the first level of
vows
the first set that you accept is called
this
means individual
Freedom one for he for
freedom and 100
dollars why is it called Freedom one
by one individual
Freedom We have so much money dear
this is a mental path to
nerves What does one for
one against
against you told me about it is 50
dollars and I need part of the prati Why
one for
one
dogs those individuals who take these vows
will receive freedom
and you give me an answer for 25 to she for
50 so they reached 100 dollars But this is for
no one but I do not give them to anyone
I am not so wild generous I make deals
So it means
if if you
protect the vows keep them you tear And if
you do not keep the
vows that is why they are called
individual individual freedom
[music]
individual  Those who will be among them will achieve
Freedom, and those individuals who
will not keep them will not achieve Freedom.
It is clear, and here Asha
says there are seven types of ato
timosh and here such a contradiction, such a
contradiction, there are not seven of them
actually and we must explain. I
made a lesson for
you and here
Asha says he did not
include one-day vows. He said
one-day
vows are one day. What, why do we
need to count them at all? Usually we
say eight types of vows. For example,
we say one-day - these are the
first. Noti speak, but one day he thinks about this,
therefore he does not include them.
And these seven are the
first person who agreed to
keep the 10th or 8th vow throughout his life.
These are worldly
vows. Modernly, these are the first vows of a
man, and in our time, even
lifelong vows of
women are vows.
Since the time when in India women
had no rights and men had all the rights. And I
want to turn this around. And secondly, I want to
say the second - It is a man who
keeps these worldly vows. This is the first
two. The first two of the seven make a
woman and a man.  and
the third
and this is
[music] the
second nun who just
accepted and then the young
monk Mona the new monk
mo for nuns it was more difficult to become a
full
nun they had to keep vows
longer and
show that at first they had
such basic vows then average then
higher and the sixth and seventh are the vows of a
full monk and full monks
[music]
vows for a
full Mona
for nuns Why more for
nuns because they are smarter and they
can keep more
vows the nuns taught me
this we had discussions about this
gori very interesting
thing
says if you will keep one of
these seven sets of vows for example you
agreed from these vows until the end of your
life even 10B say
ready for the vow
bassa understand what happened in this
room those who
dream dreams of taking vows in the
place where the emperor took vows in China
mom need to take other ponies
because you
must take other vows you cannot
take vows bassa If you do not take
these basic vows it is easy yes
Understandable  I'm trying to read you a
contract here If you want and agree
to take the 64 vows of the pos they are
very
[music]
evidence su fascinating
You must then agree to the basic
actions do not kill Do not steal Do not
mess with other people's wives or
other
people's partners You see without the basic vows you
cannot take the vows of the
bahi Tell me
that means if you have the karma to come back
here during the cherry blossom season and take the
vow sign o maybe the plane will
be delayed or your boss will say you have a
project
or or or your bank account will
go below zero like My bank account
and you have it means luck or something in this
ro if you have the luck to come to
Tibet and this I can't this is what is in your
mind What is your karma
[music]
mind it is billions of years old I don't know Maybe you
will die before March Maybe I will die before March we
don't
know that means if you have good enough
karma to be here if
you have good enough karma to
Get here we don't know
If you pray to be
here it will help  you create you understand
about the World Cup I Speak oh my God I really want this will
help you get karma be here
just to get here just to get
here you see Chinese master his
ship was destroyed five times he is a Great
master
I should not say what
word in any case you
understand if the Great master his
ship is destroyed five times And he
gets to the place to give vows
Maybe then you will have delays the
plane maybe you T fly
earlier
something you stop
well plan come
here a week in advance try to find every
French restaurant this is my
plan
how when I should stop
Stop nya When the time comes it is
said in order to receive the vows of
Bado You must
have from
includes one-day OBD and therefore
he has in
types this is a very interesting
part When you practice the secret
teaching which we call the teachings the vows of the
Diamond Way is called varana Say
varana When you practice the secret
teaching
They say if
[music]
mo monks have
you you you extra points it is
easier for you it is not
necessary to be a monk or nun
to get  secret both it is
not necessary Anyone who is in this room
can get If you have
but the highest level of success is with
monks and nuns traditionally this is so
but anyone can get Why why
Tell me According to this theory This is the whole
theory So yes the more morality
you want to keep the better you will
keep the secret vows
If you want 64 or there 360
vows we tried to translate the
vows of monks it is very difficult there for example
do not tie
your beliefs we figured out for a month What is
there I will not say What is the reason
they are very careful they are used to being
careful
in for example not tying a bag with
special some kind of string That's
why they have a better chance of being
successful with secret vows but any of
you can get secret and none of
you can
you
Diamond this is a requirement
but in
general our
people they have a
history they were
Naga these are essentially dragons
smart
[music]
dragons worldly gods who
accepted They were able to practice the teachings of
ba so it is not
necessary that you be a
human to get these vows
what is the
best in
general any kind  morality which
prepares you for
morality, it's like a special
protik. In general, you don't have to
take the batsa vows to be a
monk or monks. But those monks
who took the bahi
sat vows, their monk and monks vows are much more
powerful. They get
upgrades to business class. And what is the
first
class of the Diamond Way? Yes, the very first
class is the Diamond Way.
Some people say, well,
look, what are the lowest vows to take? The lowest vows,
say, one-day vows.
But in general, there are
five vows. I won't. I won't
kill people. I won't. Nothing
valuable. I won't have sex with my
husband or anyone else. I won't lie
about seeing emptiness. These are the
first, most basic basic
p. Tell me again.
I
agree not to take alcohol or
chemicals. According to ancient books,
alcohol, drugs, marijuana. I promise
that I will never use them in
my
life. I wasn't
born to be
Christian. I had wonderful experiences in the church,
but
many of my
friends when I started studying together.  with
your lama in nie 30
years first you can never
drink in your life You can't
drink anymore 20 years ssia per
I mean boo
Bless him
why did he say yes alcohol destroyed
my family it destroyed my mom my
dad I spent 20 years Watching how alcohol
destroyed killed my parents destroyed
my whole family and God blessed I love
Buddhism This is
cool this is a good start
If you guys say that the lowest
morality
includes never drinking any
alcohol do not take any Yes I'm with
you this is a good system because I
saw as a child What
alcohol does to two Good people it is they were
good people but alcohol made them worse
and worse
so don't come say
but what if I want to have a glass of
wine with my
[music]
grandmother for example you go Grandma She
wants you to drink
wine you pour wine for her and yourself and
then accidentally spills
your wine I've done this many times the whole floor
it's all burgundy that's
why
There is a famous exception. If you
don't want to take the vows, you don't have to
just agree to keep the
10 basic morals that everyone in
Buddhism
hurts just in your mind. Say, I will
follow ten good
deeds.
I
prefer this
list to sound positive
than negative. I don't like
saying don't kill. Don't steal. I
like
saying protect
life, protect other people's things,
respect other people's marriages, tell the
truth, always always
inspire, connect
people, always
say good, soft things, re and
there, don't talk all that blah-blah. If you can't, then keep quiet.
Don't be upset when other
people don't get
things, never when someone gets something, and
lastly, and by
Su. Follow the kar. These are positive
ten. You don't have to take the vow. If
you keep these ten, you
can still become a bahi. It's like a
cheap way to be a bahi. You don't have to take the
vows. It's clear as a
basis. I agree not to harm other
people.
What do you think the second level of ra is? The
first level of ra. The first, please, at least don't harm other people. The
second, it's easy to
help people, just help
people. We had a performance at this
main university, a national
university.  In Peru We had a
performance there We had Breakfast with the President of the
University
[music]
Iko Can I ask a question I'm like Yes what
What different types of
morality Buddhist taco glad you
asked first at least do not harm other
people then second help other
people third that we will get
there and different types of morality
to help other people here is the
list I have another 10 minutes
right This can
teach a person who turned on the ob
then goes to the temple to meet the gift When
I first entered the temple she
taught her
strongly Don't you know how to meet the
temple I was like
you don't know how to meet the temple and
how do you meet the temple first of all you need to like this
he hit me like that It
was the first
day I don't know
[music]
his I don't know whether his hand is worn out or
my
head is so stupid even t sde vre
with the gift we don't say visit the temple we
say meet the
gift va thumbs inside you have a
problem like this you were born like an animal
you fold your thumbs like this and
you walk
around glad to meet you Tara ra meet  with
you, oh, you look cool and so yes,
just doing this is the second type of
morality, just holding your hands
correctly is the second type of
morality, showing
respect, showing respect to the teacher and
other students is basic
morality, the second
level, sitting on the lase, here in such
classes, this is the second
type because you create good,
just si Here you create good karma,
even if you fall asleep during classes, you
create good
karma, this is good
karma, busy law
[music]
and think and think like this,
think on the plane, for example, or on the way
back and think about what you
heard, this is also
morality, this is Buddhist
[music]
morality and then
later
Tell me, we must teach You must
teach
There is an agreement of wild scholars, there is a
basic basic contract between teacher
and student and we have been in class for 2 years now if you are in
class here inside just sitting
in class you agreed to teach
later You are not allowed to be in class
If you do not agree to teach, you do not
listen 100 dollars
where G gave his first Buddhist
teachings
Masha's nepra is cancelled 100
dollars
this this
was If you know om this
[music]
this is a small
Vagen Yes it was a
lot big Vagen I
say
small
only fits one
person and my first lesson it was
he came to me he is half mo two me a
question onco I gave you money for last
time in America By the way you shouldn't give
money to the postman But if you don't give them
money sometimes it doesn't get through I'm just
telling
about in any case no no
guys what are you doing here This is a Buddhist
Buddhist
temple we study Buddhism here he is like Can
I study Buddhism I am like Are
you serious he is like yes and he was my
first student I am like Can I asked
the teacher Can I teach him in the
kitchen he is like No I don't want Poli
he was here he is like go to
Chita he is sitting behind you are sitting with and you
teach it is very hard on the neck
when I say you must teach
Buddhism You must teach
ri because you have studied I
mean also
coffee also at the table with  family on New
Year and something like that
And you need to
eat there Rani not in this way you teach
just inspire other people to be
good people then you teach Buddhism
this is how you
start you just prepare a dish
for dinner make such a dinner there for the day on
Thanksgiving Day and then
says By the way, do you think It's okay to
kill Are they alive or not very softly
gently teach this
and this is it Chen teach
Buddhism even to a friend in the
car it doesn't
mean it will take me 50 years to
find you
re you won't find 250
people weeks don't
think they can't get away from you
you ducked well So let me
tell you about
morality called the second level of
morality
all attempts to study the six perfections whether
you are trying to help yourself or other
people are
morality all
attempts to study the six activities of Bahi
are
morality in English or in
Russian usually stn cheat don't kill
other people there don't eat don't drive
your Tesla
100m in
and here I have One Chinese man bought a
car didn't know how fast his
car could go Well okay I won't
embarrass but I think I already embarrassed him So the
next
[music]
sentence all the activity ba
refers to one of the TX types of morality
just coming to class Amri classes on the
steps of the path just studying the steps of the path in
itself is
morality just studying the steps of the
path in
this class For 40 years Every time
you sat there you practiced
morality is morality being a
good person is morality
I have 2 more minutes
m the third level of morality the first is
just avoiding harming other people the
second is trying to help other people and the
third is helping everyone in the world trying to
help everyone in the
world
there is a special practice for this is
called
[music]
Repeat this four
ways to treat your
students
these are the famous four ways How to
treat with court They are very
beautiful If you are in this
class You have a moral
responsibility to share this with others
and Buddhism we speak if they
want it Okay if they want it we are not
allowed to bother other people of
our religion Oh you are a Jew And you want to know
about Buddhism I am the one who will tell you about
it No actually I don't want to know about it
and how Be we should we are not
allowed to disturb other people
those people who do not want to listen about it
you need to ask so nicely and
softly do you
want to hear what I heard in
Kyoto he is like no I write to my mother
taco you are like Okay and I want to study
then we have a responsibility to share
this with others it makes a big difference where I
live
[music]
there are different release people who come
to my house jump the door my
wife my wife may not be able to say no
But I can calmly say no but she
became friends with him She is like yes come in gives
them coffee gives them cake and talks to
them It is very nice And we are not
allowed to do this so we traditionally
offer mandalas this means I want to
study please teach
me if they do not offer mandalas then
we should not teach this means no one asked
me to
teach If you flew to where you sit for a
whole
hour I assume you want to
learn something so I am comfortable
teaching you even without mandalas and traditionally
we should do mandalas now we will have a
break but when we return we
will talk about the four staffs How to
share  Free time with other people How long is the
break? 30 minutes pere because there
will be a traffic jam here. Have a
nice break.